Finding Aid for the Verne Dyson Papers LSC.0804
UCLA Library Special Collections
Verne Dyson papers
1914-1962
UCLA Library Special Collections
Dyson, Verne
LSC.0804
9.0 Linear Feet (18 boxes)
Verne Dyson (1879- ) was a feature writer for the Kansas City Star (1907), and joined the staff of the Los Angeles Times as manager of the Pasadena news bureau and Sunday editor. At the end of World War I, he went to Shanghai, China to become dean of Williams College. In 1921, he became professor of English and Chinese history at the University of the Philippines in Manila and helped to found the Philippine Academy of Social Sciences. The collection consists of correspondence, research notes, unpublished manuscripts, books, pamphlets, clippings, maps, articles, scrapbooks, student compositions, photographs, postcards, and original prints of Verne Dyson, American journalist, teacher and author.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942329663606533
Biography
Dyson was born in 1879 in Calloway County, Missouri; graduated from Central College in 1905; became the feature writer for the Kansas City Star in 1907; in the same year he joined the staff of the Los Angeles Times as manager of the Pasadena news bureau and Sunday editor; wrote a history of Los Angeles; after the end of World War I, he went to Shanghai, China to become dean of Williams College; in 1921 he became professor of English and Chinese history at the University of the Philippines in Manila and helped to found the Philippine Academy of Social Sciences; appointed director of the Chinese Studies Institute in 1933; from 1940-61 he served as curator of the Walt Whitman Museum at Huntington, New York; founded the Brentwood, New York Bulletin, and the Walt Whitman Quarterly; retired to Los Angeles in 1961; published works include the novel Black Cloth (1925), Forgotten Tales of Ancient China (1934), and Whitmanland: West Hills Memories of the Poet and His Ancestors (1960).
Biographical Narrative
Verne Dyson was born in Calloway County, Missouri, in 1879. He spent his youth and early manhood in Missouri, Clayton, New Mexico, and graduated from West Denver High School in 1900. He attended Central College, Missouri, and graduated from that institution in 1905. He entered the career of journalism and in 1907 became the feature writer for the Kansas City Star.
In 1907 Mr. Dyson joined the staff of the Los Angeles Times as manager of the Pasadena News Bureau and Sunday Editor. At this time he became interested in California history and associated himself with George W. Hazard in the Hazard Historical Association to produce a history of the Los Angeles region. When George Hazard died in 1914, Dyson purchased his extensive collection of historical materials from the Hazard family and determined to complete the history of Los Angeles. Sustained by his collecting proclivities, the Collection grew to over ten thousand items. He continued his research for the history of Los Angeles and completed a manuscript which is part of this collection.
At the close of the first World War, Dyson went to Shanghai, China, to become Dean of Williams College. In 1921 he became professor of English and Chinese history at the University of the Philippines in Manila and helped to found the Philippine Academy of Social Sciences there. He received the appointment of Director of the Chinese Studies Institute in 1933, and from 1940 to 1961 he served as Curator of the Walt Whitman Museum at Huntington, Long Island, New York. While engaged in this work, he also founded the Brentwood, New York Bulletin and the Walt Whitman Quarterly. Since 1961 Mr. Dyson has been retired and living in Los Angeles.
Verne Dyson is the author of a number of books and many articles. His literary papers described in this register include his correspondence, research notes and unpublished manuscripts as well as photographs and other related printed matter which he collected in connection with his research interests.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, research notes, unpublished manuscripts, books, pamphlets, clippings, maps, articles, scrapbooks, student compositions, photographs, postcards, and original prints of Verne Dyson, American journalist, teacher and author. Most of the papers relate to the history of China and the Philippines. Manuscripts include Ancient China; Festive China; China, Russia, and Japan in Manchuria, The Cultural Development of the Philippines, Canton, and The Life of Los Angeles, the City of the Century.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Books by Dyson (Box 1).
Manuscripts by Dyson (Boxes 1-5, 18).
Research material on China (Boxes 6-9).
Material concerning Chinese famine relief (Box 10).
Compositions by Chinese students, 1922 (Box 10).
Miscellaneous material concerning China, the Institute of Pacific Relations, and the Philippine Islands (Boxes 11-14).
Chinese pictures collected by Dyson (Boxes 15-17).
Related Material
Verne Dyson oral history transcript: Recollections / Verne Dyson, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, c1967. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Sinologists -- United States -- Archives.; Journalists -- United States -- Archives.; Dyson, Verne, 1879-1971--Archives.
- Books and Manuscripts by Verne Dyson
  - Books:
    - Forgotten Tales of Ancient China. Shanghai: The Commercial Press Limited, 1934. (Box 1)
    - Foreword, Obedience, and Who's Who in the Short Story Club, in: Short Stories Written in Shanghai By Members of the Short Story Club. Shanghai: the Oriental Press, 1924. (Box 1)
    - Secrets of the Roll, by Secretary Verne Dyson... Shanghai: the Shanghai Times, 1927. (Box 1)
    - Land of the Yellow Spring. New York: Chinese Studies Press, 1937. (Box 2)
    - Remington Typewriter School... bulletin and announcements. Shanghai, 1925. (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts:
    - Ancient China; the Myths, Proto-History and History of the Chinese People to the End of the Chou Dynasty (225 B.C.)., 689 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. illustrated. Unpublished manuscript. (Box 1)
    - Festive China; the Celestial Book of Days., 618 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections [unpublished manuscript]. (Box 2)
- Manuscripts by Verne Dyson
  - Illustrations for Festive China..., 187 leaves. Mounted illustrations with typescript & holograph captions. (Box 3)
  - The illustrations are cuttings from various publications ca. and a few photographs; China, Russia, and Japan in Manchuria., 1850-1928; 466 leaves. Bound typescript with holograph corrections. illustrated [unpublished manuscript]. (Box 3)
  - Appendices to China, Russia, and Japan in Manchuria., 506 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections [unpublished manuscript]. (Box 4)
    General note
    (see Box 3)
  - The Cultural Development of the Philippines., 231 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. illustrated [unpublished manuscript]. Both manuscripts are bound. (Box 4)
  - Canton; the City of Five Rams, 886 B.C. - A.D. 1930., 184 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections [unpublished manuscript]. (Box 5)
  - History of Macao., Variously paged. typescript, holograph, and mounted printed material. map [unpublished manuscript]. (Box 5)
- Research Material on China Compiled by Verne Dyson
  - Chiefly typescript copies of articles by various persons on historical, political, social, and cultural aspects of China, but including some printed articles and clippings. (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    Scope and Contents note
    (6 vol.) compiled from Chinese historical materials gathered in the United States, China, and the Philippines. Including clippings, typescripts, letters to Dyson, and related printed ephemera, ca. 1830-1946, arranged alphabetically by subject. See Verne Dyson's typescript note at beginning of vol.1.
    - vol.1 & vol.2. (Box 7)
    - vol.3 & vol.4. (Box 8)
    - vol.5 & vol.6. (Box 9)
- Material Concerning Chinese Famine Relief ca., 1928-1932
  - Typescript reports, maps and related printed ephemera concerning Chinese famine relief work and floods in China during the, early 1930s. (Box 10)
- Compositions by Chinese Students, 1922
  - ca. 150 handwritten compositions by Chinese students in Verne Dyson's English Class at Williams College, Shanghai, 1922. (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous Material Concerning China
  - Newspaper clippings and related printed material. (Box 11)
    re the Opium War, the Nanking Incident, Dr. Sun Yat-Sen, Shanghai, Chinese literature and social life and customs.
  - Chiefly offprints, pamphlets, brochures and related printed material concerning Chinese history, social life, customs, literature, music, the British and American consular services at Shanghai and Canton, Institution for the Chinese Blind at Shanghai, and the International Institute of the Methodist Church at Shanghai. (Box 12)
    Also included are a series of negative photographic views from some of which prints were made to illustrate Dyson's unpublished manuscripts on Chinese history.
- Miscellaneous Material Concerning China and the Institute of Pacific Relations
  - Printed and manuscript material (ca., 1940).; (In black spring binder) (Box 13)
    Including a typescript and manuscript list of American Sinologists with biographical information and excerpts from their works compiled by Dyson
  - Material relating to the 5th Biennial Conference of the Institute of Pacific Relations, held at Banff, Canada, August 14-26, 1933. (Box 13)
    Including agendas of meetings, releases of proceedings and memorabilia of the trip to the Conference, photographs, etc.
    [Dyson was a member of the Philippine delegation to this conference]
- Miscellaneous Material Concerning China and the Philippine Islands
  - Maps, manuscripts and printed material. (Box 14)
    Including mounted and large folded maps of China, typescript material with chronology relating to Chinese drama, two typescripts by Dyson containing holograph corrections and in binders: Pre-Spanish Relations Between China and the Philippine Islands
  - Sino-Russian Relations, A.D., 1206-1930. (Box 14)
- Chinese Pictures Collected by Verne Dyson
  - Ca. 1000 pictures., [Photographs, post cards, clippings from newspapers and periodicals, and some original prints. Mounted on 8.5 × 11 paper and in envelopes]. (Box 15, Box 16, Box 17)
    The pictures cover the whole range of Chinese history from earliest times to ca. 1940 and include views of persons, places, emperors, buildings, landscapes, temples, etc.
- Manuscripts by Verne Dyson: History of Los Angeles
  - v.p., The Life of Los Angeles, the City of the Century. 1914-1962.; 527 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. [unpublished manuscript]. (Box 18)
    Written between 1914 and 1962 in various parts of the world. The manuscript is based largely on the collection of early Los Angeles resident, George W. Hazard which he had assembled for the purpose of writing a history, and which Dyson purchased from the Hazard Family after the death of George Hazard [See rare book catalog, Special Collections: George W. Hazard. History of Los Angeles and Vicinity... [prospectus]